Why do people deliberately destroy cultural heritage?
لماذا يقومُ الناس عمداً بتدمير التراث الثقافي؟
By doing so,
بفعلهم ذلك،
do they believe they're erasing our history?
هل يعتقدون أنهم يمحون تاريخنا؟
Our cultural memory?
ذاكرتنا الثقافية؟
It's true that we are losing cultural heritage to erosion
فالحقيقة اننا نخسرُ التراث الثقافي نتيجة التآكل،
and natural disasters,
والكوارث الطبيعية،
but this is something that is simply difficult to avoid.
ولكنه شيء من الصعب تفاديه بكل سهولة.
I'm here to show you today how we can use pictures --
ســأريكم اليوم كيف نستطيع استخدام الصور،
your pictures --
صوركم،
to reclaim the history that is being lost
لاستعادة التاريخ الذي تمّ فقدانه
using innovative technology
باستخدام تقنية مبتكره
and the effort of volunteers.
وجهود المتطوعين.
In the early 20th century,
في أوائل القرن الـ20،
archaeologists discovered hundreds of statues and artifacts
اكتشف علماء الآثار مئات من التماثيل والتحف
at the ancient city of Hatra,
في مدينة الحضر القديمة،
in northern Iraq.
في شمال العراق.
Statues like this one were found in fragments,
تم العثور على واحدٍ من هذه التماثيل كشظايا،
some of them missing their heads or arms,
يفتقدُ بعضها رؤوسها أو أذرعها،
yet the clothing that they are wearing
ولكن الملابس التي يرتدونها
and their pose
وطريقة وقوفهم أو جلوسهم
can still tell us their story.
لا تزالُ تخبرنا بقصتهم.
For example,
مثلاً،
we believe that by wearing a knee-length tunic
نحن نعتقد أنه بارتداء ملابس فضفاضة لحد الركبة
and open bare feet,
وأقدام مفتوحة عارية،
this was representative of a priest.
كان يمثلُ هذا كاهنًا.
However, with a closer look at this particular piece,
ومع ذلك، مع نظرة فاحصة لهذه القطعة تحديدًا،
we can see that this tunic being worn was elaborately decorated,
نستطيع أن نرى أن هذا الرداء الذي تم ارتداؤه قد زُخرف بشكل متقن،
which has led many researchers to believe
مما دفع العديد من الباحثين إلى الاعتقاد
this was actually a statue of a king performing his religious functions.
بأن هذا التمثال كان في الواقع لملك يؤدي وظائفه الدينية.
When the Mosul Cultural Museum opened in 1952 in northern Iraq,
عندما تم افتتاح متحف الموصل الثقافي في عام 1952 في شمال العراق،
this statue, as well as others,
هذا التمثال، إضافة إلى تماثيل أخرى،
were placed there to preserve them for future generations.
وُضعت هناك للحفاظ عليها من أجل الأجيال المستقبلية.
Following the US-led invasion of Iraq in 2003,
بعد اجتياح العراق بقيادة أمريكا عام 2003،
a few statues and artifacts were relocated to Baghdad,
تم نقل عدد قليل من التماثيل والتحف الى بغداد،
but this statue remained.
ولكن بقي هذا التمثال في مكانه.
Then in February of last year, a video was released,
ثم في فبراير/شباط من العام الماضي، تم إصدار فيديو،
and it instantly went viral.
وانتشر على الفور،
Maybe some of you remember seeing it.
ربما يتذكرُ البعض منكم مشاهدته.
Here's a short clip.
إليكم مقطع قصير.
(Video) (Singing in Arabic)
(فيديو) (إنشاد باللغة العربية)
(Singing ends)
(نهاية الإنشاد)
Not a very pleasant sight, right?
أليس هذا مشهدًا لطيفًا حقًا؟
Did you notice anything familiar in the video?
هل لاحظتم أي شيء مألوف في الفيديو؟
There it is.
هذا هو.
There is that very statue,
هذا هو التمثال ذاته،
as it was toppled over,
كما تم الإطاحة به،
breaking into pieces.
وتحطيمه إلى قطع.
When Matthew Vincent and I saw this video,
حينما شاهدت أنا وماثيو فنسنت الفيديو،
we were shocked.
كنا في حالة صدمة.
Since we are archaeologists using innovative technology
وبما أننا علماء آثار نستخدمُ التقنية المبتكرة
for digital preservation,
للحفظ الرقمي،
an idea sprung to mind.
خطرت في بالي فكره.
Maybe we can crowdsource the images that were taken of these artifacts
ربما نستطيع جمع الصور التي تم أخذها لهذه القطع الأثرية
before they were destroyed,
قبل أن يتم تدميرها،
to create digital reconstructions.
لإعادة البناء الرقمي لها.
If we can do that,
لو استطعنا فعل ذلك،
maybe we can put them into a virtual museum
ربما أمكننا وضعها في متاحف افتراضية
to tell that story.
لإخبارنا تلك القصة.
And so two weeks after we saw this video,
وبعد أسبوعين من مشاهدتنا لهذا الفيديو،
we started the project called Project Mosul.
بدأنا بالمشروع المُسمى مشروع الموصل.
Remember the pictures of the statue I showed you before?
هل تتذكرون صور التمثال الذي شاهدتموه من قبل؟
This is actually the crowdsourced reconstruction of it
هذا هو في الحقيقة إعادة بناء له استنادًا على معلومات من الجماهير عبر الإنترنت
before it was destroyed.
قبل أن يتم تدميره.
Now, many of you may be wondering,
الآن، قد يتساءل العديد منكم،
how exactly does this work?
كيف تعمل هذه التقنية بالتحديد؟
Well, the key to this technology is called photogrammetry,
حسناً، المفتاح الأساسي لهذه التقنية تدعى المسح التصويري،
and it was invented here, in Germany.
وتم اختراعها هنا، في ألمانيا.
It is the technology that allows us to use two-dimensional images
إنها تقنية تسمح لنا استخدام صُور ثنائية الأبعاد
taken of the same object from different angles
أخذت لنفس الشيء من زاويا مختلفة
to create a 3D model.
لبناء نموذج ثلاثي الأبعاد.
I know you may be thinking this sounds like magic -- but it's not.
أعلم أنكم ربما تعتقدون بأن الأمر يبدو كالسحر، لكنه ليس كذلك.
Let me show you how it works.
دعوني أُريكم كيف تعمل.
Here are two crowdsourced images of the same statue.
هاتان صورتان تجميعيتان لنفس التمثال استنادًا على معلومات الجمهور.
What the computer can do
ما يمكنُ للحاسوب القيام به
is it can detect similar features between the photographs --
هو أنه يستطيع كشف الميزات المتماثلة بين الصور،
similar features of the object.
الميزات المتماثلة للشيء.
Then, by using multiple photos,
ثم، باستخدام صور متعددة،
in this case, it can begin to reconstruct the object in 3D.
في هذه الحالة، يستطيع الحاسوب البدء بإعادة بناء الشيء بصورة ثلاثية الأبعاد.
In this case,
في هذه الحالة،
you have the position of the cameras when each image was taken,
لديكم موقع الكاميرات عندما تم التقاط كل صورة،
shown in blue.
كما هو موضح بالأزرق.
Now, this is a partial reconstruction, I admit,
الآن، أعترفُ لكم أن هذا هو إعادة بناء جزئي،
but why would I say partial?
ولكن لماذا أقول جزئي؟
Well, simply because the statue was positioned against a wall.
حسناً، لمجرد أن الثمثال وُضع مقابل الحائط.
We don't have photographs taken of it from the back.
ليس لدينا صور أُخذت له من الخلف.
If I wanted to complete a full digital reconstruction of this statue,
لو أردتُ إعادة بناء صورة رقمية كاملة لهذا التمثال،
I would need a proper camera,
سأحتاج إلى كاميرا مناسبة،
tripods, proper lighting,
مِنصَب ثلاثي القوائم، وإضاءة مناسبة.
but we simply can't do that with crowdsourced images.
لكننا ببساطة لا نستطيعُ القيام بذلك مع صور التعهيد الجماعي.
Think about it:
فكروا بالأمر:
How many of you, when you visit a museum,
كم منكم، عندما تزورون متحفًا،
take photographs of all parts of the statue,
يلتقطُ صورًا لجميع أجزاء التمثال
even the back side of it?
حتى الجانب الخلفي منه؟
Well, maybe if some of you find Michelangelo's David interesting,
حسنًا، قد يجدُ بعضكم تمثال داوود/ديفيد لمايكل أنجلو مثيرًا للاهتمام،
I guess --
أعتقدُ --
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But the thing is,
ولكن الأمر كالتالي،
if we can find more images of this object,
لو استطعنا إيجاد صور إضافية لهذا الشيء،
we can improve the 3D model.
نستطيع تطوير نموذج ثلاثي الأبعاد.
When we started the project,
عندما بدأنا المشروع،
we started it with the Mosul Museum in mind.
وضعنا في الاعتبار متحف الموصل.
We figured we may get a few images,
اعتقدنا أنه قد نحصل على عدة صورة،
some people interested,
بعض الناس المهتمين،
make one or two virtual reconstructions,
يصنعون صورة أو اثنتين لإعادة البناء الافتراضي،
but we had no idea that we had sparked something that would grow so quickly.
ولكن لم يكن لدينا أي فكرة أننا أثرنا شيئًا من شأنه أن ينمو بسرعة.
Before we knew it,
قبل أن نعلم بذلك،
we realized it was obvious:
أدركنا أنه كان واضحاً:
we could apply this same idea to lost heritage anywhere.
نستطيع تطبيق نفس الفكرة فيما يتعلق بالتاريخ المفقود في أي مكان.
And so, we decided to change the name of the project to Rekrei.
وهكذا، قررنا تغير اسم المشروع إلى ريكري.
Then, in the summer of last year,
ثم، في صيف العام الماضي،
"The Economist" magazine's media lab reached out to us.
تواصل معنا مختبر الاعلام التابع لمجلة ذا إيكونوميست،
They asked us,
وسألونا،
"Hey, would you like us to build a virtual museum
"مرحباً، هل ترغبون أن نبني متحفًا افتراضيًا
to put the reconstructions back inside,
لوضع النماذج المعاد بناؤها في الداخل،
to tell the story?"
لتخبر القصص؟"
Can you imagine us saying no?
هل يمكنكم أن تتخيلو أننا قلنا لا؟
Of course not.
بالطبع لا.
We said yes!
قلنا نعم!
We were so excited.
كنا في غاية الحماس.
This was exactly the initial dream of that project.
كان هذا بالضبط الحلم الأولي لهذا المشروع.
And so now,
والآن،
any of you can experience RecoVR Mosul on your phone,
يستطيع أي أحدٍ منكم أن يجرب الواقع الافتراضي للموصل عبر هاتفه،
using Google Cardboard
باستخدام الصندوق الكرتوني لجوجل
or a tablet or even YouTube 360.
أو أي جهاز لوحي أو حتى على يوتيوب 360.
Here is a screenshot from the virtual museum.
هذه لقطة شاشة المتحف الافتراضي
And there it is ...
وهناك ...
the partial reconstruction of the statue,
إعادة البناء الجزئي للتمثال،
as well as the Lion of Mosul,
وأيضاً أسد الموصل،
the first reconstruction completed by our project.
أول إعادة بناء بالكامل من خلال مشروعنا.
Although the video doesn't explicitly show the Lion of Mosul being destroyed,
على الرغم من أن الفيديو لا يظهر بوضوح أن أسد الموصل تم تدميره،
we have many other examples of large artifacts being destroyed
لدينا العديد من الأمثلة الأخرى لقطع أثرية كبيرة تم تدميرها
that were simply too large to have been stolen.
التي كانت ببساطة كبيرة جدًا ويصعبُ سرقتها.
For example,
مثلاً،
the Gate of Nimrud in northern Iraq.
بوابة النمرود في شمال العراق.
This is a digital reconstruction from before,
هذه صورة رقمية لإعادة بنائها من قبل،
and this is actually during the destruction.
وهذه هي في الواقع خلال التدمير.
Or the Lion of Al-LÄt, in Palmyra, Syria:
أو أسد اللات في مدينة تدمر في سوريا:
before ...
قبل ...
and after.
وبعد.
Although virtual reconstructions are primarily the main focus
على الرغم من أن إعادة البناء الافتراضي هو في الأساس التركيز الرئيسي
of our project,
لمشروعنا،
some people have been asking the question:
يطرحُ بعض الناس السؤال:
Can we print them in 3D?
هل نستطيع طباعتها بشكل ثلاثي الأبعاد؟
We believe 3D printing doesn't offer a straightforward solution
نعتقد أن الطباعة ثلاثية الأبعاد لا تقدم حلاً جيدًا
to lost heritage.
فيما يتعلق بالتراث المفقود.
Once an object is destroyed,
حال تدمير أي شيء،
it's gone.
فإنه ضاع.
But 3D printing does offer an addition to tell that story.
ولكن تقدمُ الطباعة ثلاثية الأبعاد إضافة لإخبار القصة.
For example, I can show you here ...
مثلاً، يمكنني أن أُريكم هنا ...
There is the statue from Hatra
هذا هو تمثال من مدينة الحضر
and the Lion of Mosul.
وأسد الموصل.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you.
شكرًا لكم.
Now, if you look closely,
الآن، إذا نظرتم عن كثب،
you'll notice that there are some parts that have been printed in color,
ستلاحظون أن هناك بعض الأجزاء تمت طباعتها بالألوان،
and some parts that are in white or gray.
وبعض الأجزاء بالأبيض أو الرمادي.
This part was added simply to hold the statues up.
تمت إضافة هذا الجزء ببساطة لدعم التمثال.
This works the same way if you visit a museum,
يعمل هذه الأمر تماماً إذا زرتم متحفًا،
and a statue is found in fragments;
وتم إيجاد التمثال على شكل شظايا،
it's put together for the people to see it.
توضعُ معًا ليراها الناس.
This makes sense, right?
أليس هذا منطقيًا؟
However, we're much more interested
ومع ذلك، نحن مهتمون بشكل أكبر
in what virtual reality has to offer for lost heritage.
بما يقدمه الواقع الافتراضي للتراث المفقود.
Here is an example of one of the tower tombs
هذا مثال لأحد أبراج المقابر
that was destroyed in Palmyra.
التي تم تدميرها في تدمر.
Using Sketchfab's online viewer,
باستخدام منصة العرض Sketchfab عبر الإنترنت
we can show that we have reconstructed three parts of the exterior of the tomb,
نستطيعُ أن نظهر أننا أعدنا بناء ثلاثة أجزاء خارجية للقبر،
but we also have photos of the inside,
ولكن لدينا أيضاً صور من الداخل،
so we're beginning to create a reconstruction of the wall
لذلك، بدأنا بإعادة بناء الحائط،
and the ceiling.
والسقف.
Archaeologists worked there for many, many years,
عمل علماء الآثار هناك لسنوات عديدة جدًا،
so we also have architectural drawing plans of this lost heritage.
لذلك لدينا أيضًا رسوم معمارية لهذا التراث المفقود.
Unfortunately, we are not only losing cultural heritage to areas of conflict
للأسف، نحن لا نفقد التراث الثقافي في مناطق الصراع
and at war --
وفي الحرب فقط،
we're also losing it to natural disasters.
نحن نفقدها كذلك نتيجة الكوارث الطبيعية.
This is a 3D model of Durbar Square in Kathmandu,
هذا هو نموذج ثلاثي الأبعاد لساحة دوربار في كاتاماندر،
before the earthquake that occurred last April ...
قبل الزلزال الذي حدث في أبريل/نيسان الماضي...
and this is after.
وهذا بعد.
You may be thinking,
قد تفكرون،
you didn't create these 3D models with only tourist photographs,
لم نقم بإنشاء هذه النماذج ثلاثية الأبعاد بواسطة الصور السياحية فقط،
and that's true.
وهذا صحيح.
But what this represents
ولكن ما يمثله هذا
is the ability for large, public organizations and private industry
هو قدرة المنظمات الكبيرة العامة، والقطاعات الخاصة
to come together for initiatives like ours.
لتتعاون معًا من أجل مبادرات مثل مبادرتنا.
And so one of the major challenges of our project, really,
وإحدى أكبر التحديات لمشروعنا بالفعل
is to find photographs that were taken before something happens, right?
هي العثور على صور تم التقاطها قبل أن يحدث شيء، صحيح؟
Well, the internet is basically a database with millions of images, right?
حسنا، الإنترنت هو في الأساس قاعدة بيانات تحوي الملايين من الصور، أليس كذلك؟
Exactly.
بالضبط.
So we have begun to develop a tool
لذلك بدأنا في تطوير أداة
that allows us to extract images from websites like Flickr,
تسمح لنا باستخراج الصور من مواقع مثل فليكر،
based on their geotags,
بناءً على علاماتها الجغرافية،
to complete reconstructions.
لاستكمال إعادة البناء.
Because we're not only losing cultural heritage to natural disasters and in war,
لأننا لا نخسر التراث الثقافي نتيجة الكوارث الطبيعية والحرب فقط،
but we're also losing it to something else.
ولكننا نخسرها بسبب شيء آخر.
Any idea, just looking at these two pictures?
هل لديكم أي فكره بمجرد النظر لهاتين الصورتين؟
Maybe it's a little difficult to remember,
ربما من الصعب قليلًا أن نتذكر،
but only a few weeks ago,
ولكن قبل بضعة أسابيع فقط،
this was the example of human destruction by human stupidity.
كان ذلك مثالًا للتدمير البشري من قبل الغباء البشري.
Because a tourist in Lisbon wanted to climb onto this statue
لأن أحد السياح في لشبونه أراد تسلق التمثال
and take a selfie with it --
وأخذ صورة ملتقطة شخصيًا معه،
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
and pulled it down with him.
وسحبه معه إلى أسفل.
So we're already finding photographs
فوجدنا بالفعل صورًا
to complete a digital reconstruction of this.
لإكمال البناء الرقمي لهذا التمثال.
We need to remember
نحن بحاجة لأن نتذكر
that the destruction of cultural heritage isn't a recent phenomenon.
أن تدمير التراث الثقافي ليس ظاهرة حديثة.
In the 16th century,
في القرن السادس عشر،
European priests and explorers burned thousands of Maya books in the Americas,
أحرق الكهنة والمستكشفون الأوروبيون الآلاف من كتب حضارة المايا في الأمريكتين،
of which we only have a handful left.
ولم يبق لدينا سوى حفنة قليلة.
Fast-forward to 2001,
عودة سريعة لعام 2001،
when the Taliban blew up the Bamiyan Buddhas in Afghanistan.
عندما فجرت طالبان تمثال بوذا في وادي باميان في افغانستان.
You see,
كما تعلمون،
cultural heritage is about our shared global history.
فالتراث الثقافي هو حول تاريخنا العالمي المشترك.
It helps us connect with our ancestors and their stories,
يساعدنا على التواصل مع أسلافنا وقصصهم،
but we're losing pieces of it every day to natural disasters
ولكننا نخسر أجزاء منه كل يوم نتيجة الكوارث الطبيعية
and in areas of conflict.
وفي مناطق الصراع.
Of course, the loss of human life is the most heartbreaking loss ...
طبعاً، فقدان الحياة البشرية هي أكثر الخسارات المحزنة...
but cultural heritage offers us a way to preserve the memory of the people
ولكن يقدمُ لنا التراث الثقافي وسيلة للحفاظ على ذاكرة الشعب
for future generations.
للأجيال المستقبلية.
We need your help to reclaim the history that is being lost.
نحن بحاجة لمساعدتكم لاستعادة التاريخ الذي يتم فقدانه.
Will you join us?
هل ستنضمون إلينا؟
(Applause)
(تصفيق)